Guide to the Deutsche Verein Records, 1909 - 1960
Deutsche Verein Records, 1909 - 1960
Special Collections & Archives, Wesleyan University
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Deutsche Verein.
1000-139
0.25
1
Der Deutsche Verein, or The German Club, was a student organization at Wesleyan whose purpose was to promote the learning and application of the German language.
The collection includes two secretary's books, programs from theater performances, invitations, creative writing, and materials from the Golden Anniversary Celebration in 1960.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
No restrictions.
Acquisitions Information
Probably acquired circa 1969.
Historical Note
Der Deutsche Verein, or The German Club, was a student organization at Wesleyan whose purpose was to promote the learning and application of the German language. The members were students with a high level of German, generally past the second level or higher. Membership was limited to 25 members at a time, and members were required to be highly active and pay dues. They held elections and elected officers for various posts including president, vice-president, and secretary. They held regular meetings on the first and third Saturday of every month of the school year around 7:00 pm.
Their gatherings (Sitzungen) frequently included meals, and very often they were accompanied by faculty and students reading essays, stories, and poems written in German, of all academic subjects, and pertaining to German Studies, such as travels in Germany, and post-war era topics. They also held a yearly Christmas party (Weihnachtsfest) on December 8 with a large feast, gifts, singing, and readings of verses and poetry.
Collection Overview
Almost the entire collection is in German, except for two documents.
The collection contains two secretary's books, covering the years 1909-1920 and 1946-1955, with the minutes and protocols from the meetings, the group's constitution, and various mementos from the given dates. Photos and invitations to the group's theater performance in 1910 are also included. The folder with miscellaneous documents from 1931 to 1938 contains a program for another play put on in 1930, and an invitation to the Christmas party in 1938. Of particular interest is a short story dated 1934 by T.M. Campbell about an American who wakes in the forest to stumble upon the cottage of Goethe, and has a somewhat mystical encounter with him where the famous writer reveals some of his writing genius.
Finally, there are two folders dedicated to the Golden Anniversary of the club in 1960. One folder contains the speeches of L.E. Gemeinhardt and Sten Flygt given in English, and almost 80 telegrams and letters from former members on the occasion in both German and English. The guest book from the occasion is also included.
Collection Arrangement
The materials are arranged chronologically.
Online Catalog Headings
These and related materials may be found under the following headings in online catalogs.
Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.). Deutsche Verein.; Wesleyan University (Middletown, Conn.)--Students.; German language -- Study and teaching -- United States.
Detailed Description of the Collection
  - Secretary's Book, 1909-1920 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Includes all minutes from the meetings during this period, lists of officers and members, protocols, and versions of the group constitution from 1909, 1913, and 1920, respectively.
  - Dramatische Abend (Dramatic Evening) event, 1910 (Folder 2)
    This event was held in Fayerweather Gymnasium on June 8, 1910 for productions of Wie es dich gefaellt (As You Like It) by William Shakespeare and Die Hochzeitsreise (The Honeymoon) by Roderich Benedix.
    - Invitation and program
    - 1 black-and-white photo of Wie es dich gefaellt
    - 1 black and white photo of Die Hochzeitsreise
  - Documents, 1931-1938 (Folder 3)
    - Program, May 20, 1930 for Der Deutsche Verein and La Societe Francais present Alexander Wilhemi's Einer Muss Heiraten and Moliere's Le Borgeois Gentilhomme
    - Short story by T.M. Campbell, 1934 about encounter with Goethe
      About an American who wakes in the forest to stumble upon the cottage of Goethe, and has a somewhat mystical encounter with him where the famous writer reveals some of his writing genius.
    - Invitation to Christmas Party (Deutscher Verein Weihnachtssitzung) Thursday, December 15, 1938
  - Secretary's Book 1946-1955: Das Protokoll und der Kassenbericht (Folder 4)
    Includes minutes and protocols from all the meetings, lists of members and officers, club rules, and poetry by Wesleyan professor of German L. E. Gemeinhardt
  - Volume, Letters of Observance on the Golden Anniversary May 7, 1960 (Folder 5)
    - Speech in English by L.E. Gemeinhardt
    - Speech in English by guest speaker Sten Flygt (Ph.D. and Wesleyan class of 1932) entitled Foreign Language Study: Satisfactions and Rewards
    - Approximately 75-80 telegrams, letters, and postcards from former members of the club some written in German and some in English.
  - Guestbook from the Golden Anniversary May 7, 1960 (Folder 6)
  - Handwritten summary of Deutsche Verein club records, April 18, 1969 (Folder 7)
  - Undated poems in German about Wesleyan University